A Guide to the Connecticut Political Collections 1980.0006
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
Connecticut Political Collections
undated, 1827-2004
1968-2004
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1980.0006
4.25 Linear Feet
The collection is an artificial one created to gather together pieces of politically related materials that are not cohesive collections in and of themselves. Presently, the collection contains political posters, printed ephemera, realia, photographs, a video recording and published speeches and one manuscript.
Biography
Jimmy Carter and Walter Mondale were the democratic party candidates for the 1976 Presidential Election. Carter is the recipient of the 2002 Nobel Peace Prize and served two terms in the Georgia Senate and as the 76th Governor of Georgia (1971-1975) before being elected President. Mondale was a two term senator from Minnesota prior to his election as Vice President.
Emilio Q. Daddario (b. September 24, 1918) of Middletown, Connecticut, served in the U.S. Army during World War II; mayor of Middletown, Conn. (1946-1948); state court judge in Connecticut (1948-1950); major in the U.S. Army during the Korean conflict; U.S. Representative from Connecticut 1st District (1959-1971).
Gerald Ford was the 38th President of the United States, serving from 1974 to 1977, and the 40th Vice President of the United States serving from 1973 to 1974. He was the first person appointed to the vice-presidency under the terms of the 25th Amendment, and became President upon Richard Nixon's resignation. Before his election as Vice President, Ford served nearly 25 years as Representative from Michigan's 5th congressional district, eight of them as the Republican Minority Leader.
Hubert H. Humphrey, Jr. (1911-1978) of Minneapolis, Minnesota, served as delegate to Democratic National Convention from Minnesota (1944, 1948, 1960); mayor of Minneapolis, Minn. (1945-1948); U.S. Senator from Minnesota (1949-1964, 1971-1978); candidate for Democratic nomination for Vice President (1956); candidate for Democratic nomination for President (1960, 1972); Vice President of the United States (1965-1969); Democratic candidate for President of the United States (1968).
Lyndon Baines Johnson (1908-1973) served as U.S. Representative from Texas 10th District (1937-1949); delegate to Democratic National Convention from Texas (1940); U.S. Senator from Texas (1949-1961); candidate for Democratic nomination for President (1956, 1968); Vice President of the United States (1961-1963); President of the United States (1963-1969).
Edith Prague of Columbia, Connecticut. A former social worker and school teacher, Prague serves as a member of Connecticut state house of representatives; member of Connecticut state senate 19th District (1995-).
Richard M. Nixon was the 37th President of the United States (1969–1974) and the only president to ever resign the office. He was also the 36th Vice President of the United States (1953–1961). In 1946 he was elected as a Republican to the House of Representatives representing California's 12th Congressional district, then in 1950 was elected to the United States Senate. He served as Vice President under Dwight D. Eisenhower before running unsuccessfully in the 1960 presidential election and 1962 California gubernatorial election.
Abraham Ribicoff (1910-1998) of Hartford, Connecticut. Member of Connecticut state house of representatives from Hartford (1939-1942); state court judge in Connecticut (1941-1943), 1945-1947); U.S. Representative from Connecticut 1st District (1949-1953); Governor of Connecticut (1955-1961); U.S. Secretary of Health, Education and Welfare (1961-1962); U.S. Senator from Connecticut (1963-1981).
Gloria Schaffer born in New London, Connecticut on October 3, 1930. Member of Connecticut state senate; secretary of state of Connecticut (1971-1978); candidate for U.S. Senator from Connecticut (1976).
Gideon Tomlinson (1780-1854) of Fairfield, Connecticut. A lawyer by profession, he was a member of Connecticut state legislature (1817); U.S. Representative from Connecticut (at-large, 1819-1827); Governor of Connecticut (1827-1831); U.S. Senator from Connecticut (1831-1837).
John Kerry and John Edwards were the unsuccessful democratic party candidates for the 2004 presidential election. Kerry has served as a U.S. Senator from Massachusetts since 1985. He is also chairman of the Senate Foreign Relations Committee. Edwards served a single term as the U.S. Senator from North Carolina.
Nelson Rockefeller (1908-1979) served as the 41st Vice president from 1974-1977 under Gerald R. Ford. He was the Governor of New York from 1959-1973 and unsuccessfully sought the Republican presidential nomination in 1960, 1964, and 1968.
Newt Gingrich served as Congressman from Georgia from 1979 to 1999, and was the Speaker of the U.S. House of Representatives from 1995-1999. In 2012, Gingrich was a candidate for the Republican presidential nomination.
Bill Clinton and Al Gore served two terms as President and Vice President of the United States from 1993-2001. Before becoming President, Clinton was the Governor of Arkansas from 1979-1981 and 1983-1992. Prior to his time as Vice President, Gore served as a U.S. Senator from Tennessee. He later ran unsuccessfully for President in the 2000 election.
Lowell P. Weicker, Jr. was Governor of Connecticut from 1991-1995. Prior to that, he served as U.S. Senator from 1971-1989. After falling out with the increasingly conservative Republican party, Weicker ran for Governor as an Independent.
Richard Blumenthal is a current U.S. Senator from Connecticut and previously served as Connecticut's Attorney General from 1991-2011. During his twenty years as Attorney General, Blumenthal advocated on behalf of Connecticut against air pollution, tobacco, the Microsoft monopoly, and global warming, among other causes.
Al Gore unsuccessfully ran for President in 2000 with running mate Joe Lieberman from Connecticut. Despite winning the popular vote, Gore lost the election to President George W. Bush after Florida's contested electoral votes were awarded to Bush.
Additional biographical information is available at the Political Graveyard and the Biographical Directory of the U.S. Congress.
Scope and Content
The collection is an artificial one created to gather together pieces of politically related materials that are not cohesive collections in and of themselves. Presently, the collection contains political posters, printed ephemera, realia, photographs, a video recording and published speeches and one manuscript.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by format.
Series I: Manuscripts (1827)
Series II: Posters (undated, 1976, 1994)
Series III: Printed ephemera (1968, 1976)
Series IV: 2012 Accession (1968-2004)
Acquisition Information
The poster portion of the collection was donated. The manuscript letter was purchased in 1996. The materials in Series IV were donated in September 2012.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Correspondence; Speeches (documents); Posters; Politicians; Printed ephemera; Ford, Gerald R., 1913-2006.; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978.; Curran, Hugh.; Daddario, Emilio Q. (Emilio Quincy), 1918-2010; Cardin, Mike.; Carter, Jimmy, 1924-.; Tomlinson, Gideon, 1780-1854; Schaffer, Gloria; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994; Prague, Edith; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973.; Mondale, Walter F., 1928-; Ribicoff, Abraham, 1910-1988
- Series I: Manuscript, 1827
  - Barker, Perrin to Governor Gideon Tomlinson, 1827 December 23 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II: Posters, undated, 1976, 1994
  - State Office
    - Cardin, Mike, undated (Box OS)
    - Curran, Hugh, undated (Box OS)
    - Prague, Edith, 1994 (Box OS)
  - National Office
    - Daddario, Emilio (House), undated (Box OS)
    - Johnson/Humphrey, undated (Box OS)
    - McCarthy/Peace, undated (Box OS)
    - Ribicoff, Abraham (Senate), undated (Box OS)
    - Schaffer, Gloria (Senate), 1976 (Box OS)
- Series III: Ephemera, 1968, 1976
  - Carter, Jimmy and Mondale, Walter, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ford, Gerald, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Nixon, Richard (Speeches), 1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series IV: 2012 Accession, undated, 1968-2004
  - Ephemera, realia, manuscripts, clippings, moving images, photographs, correspondence, undated, 1968-2004 (Box 2)
    Scope and Content Note
    [Subjects include: Content focuses on national democratic campaigns (Clinton/Gore, Gore/Lieberman, and Kerry/Edwards) with the exception of Republican Nelson Rockefeller's campaigns in the 1960s and several local Connecticut politicians in the 1990s.]